<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of unwryten verytyes</title>
            <author>Smith, Richard, 1500-1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22823</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102260</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838050</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838050</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2407</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12495)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2407)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1433:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of unwryten verytyes</title>
                  <author>Smith, Richard, 1500-1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In saynct Andrewes Paryshe in the Waredrop by Thomas Raynalde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.XLVIII.] [1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Richard Smith.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum priuilegio.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2407:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2407:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Of vnwry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten very tyes <hi>Cum priuilegio,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2407:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Of vnwrytten very tyes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the day of Pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tecoſt wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy gooſt deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the apoſtles &amp; diſcyples of Chryſt, they receyued ſuche grace &amp; gooſtly knowlege, that they hade forth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the gyfte of the vnderſtandynge of ſcrypture: and to ſpeake in the tonges of all men. And al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo that vpon whome ſoeuer they layde theyr handes, the holye ghoſte ſhoulde deſcende vpon them. And ther vpon they by theyr prechyng &amp; good doctryn co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhort tyme, great multitude of people vnto the fayth of Chriſt And after that dyuers bleſſed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrength of the fayth, wrote the lyfe, miracles, do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctryne, paſſion deth, and reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our mayſter Chryſt: but foure of thoſe writinges were only receyued by al the hole chyrche of Chryſt. that is to ſay, of
<pb facs="tcp:2407:2"/>
Matthewe. Marke, Luke &amp; Ihon. &amp; they receyued them to be of ſuch aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhould not be lawfull to any man, that wold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe Chryſt, to denye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; they were called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foure goſpels of Chriſt. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> epyſtles of Paule, the Actes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles, the epiſtles that be called canonyke. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apocalips were receyued to be of lyke auctorytye, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpels were. And thus by aſſent aſwel of the people, as of the clergye, was the newe teſtament affyrmed to be of ſuche auctorytye, as it is now take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be of, &amp; as it is of in dede. ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not lawfull to denye any thing that it affermeth, ne to afferme any thyng that it denyeth, &amp; it is no meruayle though it be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be of ſuch ſtrengthe, for it was auctory<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed whan the people that were newelye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth, were ful of grace &amp; of deuocion, repleniſhed with vertues, deſyryng alwaye the lyfe to come, &amp; the helthe of theyr owne ſoules, &amp; of theyr
<pb facs="tcp:2407:3"/>
neyghbours. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo were bleſſed biſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhops, bleſſed preeſtes, &amp; other bleſſed perſons of the clargy: and what could ſuche men aſke of god ryghtwiſly, that ſholde be denyed them. And who maye thinke, but that they &amp; al the people, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd auctoriſyng of ſcripture, praied deuoutly for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſiſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt that they might haue grace to auctoriſe ſuche thyng as ſhold be to his honour / to the encreaſe of his fayth, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helth of the ſoules of al his people. The tyme alſo that this auctoryſynge of the new teſtament, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gatherynge of it togy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der was made, was (as I ſuppoſe) the tyme of the mooſt hygh &amp; gracyous ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge out of the mercy of god into the world, that euer was fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnyng of the world vnto thys daye: &amp; I meane the tyme that was fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the incarnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt vnto the ſayd auctoryſyng of the newe teſtament was accompliſhed: for in part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme our lord was here
<pb facs="tcp:2407:3"/>
himſelfe in bodyly preſence, preachyng and teachyng his lawes / gatherynge &amp; chewſynge hys apoſtles &amp; diſciples / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſholde teache &amp; preache his lawes wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was gone: which they dyd not onely by word, but alſo by good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, that yet remayne vnto thys day: ſo that al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme may in maner be called the golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme. And not onely the newe teſtament was tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receyued, but alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And by preachyng &amp; teachyng of theſe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth of Chriſt meruaylouſly encreaſed in many coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trees. After all this, by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeking among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, the byſhops, preeſtes and other of the clergye, which were as lanternes vnto the people, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpecyall maynteyners of the chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fayth, were called the chyrche, or men of the chyrch: and vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> colour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name chyrche many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy in proces of tyme, pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tended y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might make expoſicions of ſcripture, as the vniuerſal chyrch of
<pb facs="tcp:2407:4"/>
Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of chriſten people myghte, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon whan couetyſe &amp; pryde ſomwhat encreſed in many of the clargie, they ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pounded very fauourably dyuers tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of ſcripture, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſounded to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maynte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce of theyr honour, power, iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction &amp; ryches. And ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> toke vpon them to afferme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrche that myght not erre / and that Chryſt &amp; his apoſteles had ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; taught many thynges, that were not expreſly put in ſcripture, &amp; that the people were as wel bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to beleue them, and that vnder lyke payne, as yf they had ben expreſſed in ſcripture, and called them vnwryten veryties, where of I ſhal, as for an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple recyte part. Fyrſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt after his maundye, and after he had waſſhen the fete of his apoſtles, taught them to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke holy creame, for myniſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue as ful aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytye to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, as yf it had bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned
<pb facs="tcp:2407:4"/>
in ſcriptuere, that chriſt had gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> power to it. That it is a tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtels, that ymages ought to be ſet vp. That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtels ordeyned that al faythful people ſhould reſort to the chyrch of Rome, as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt hygh and principal chyrche of al other: &amp; yet it can not be proued by ſcripture, ne by any other ſufficiente auctoritye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they made any ſuch ordynaunce. Alſo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crede, which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly &amp; vniuerſally vſed to be ſaid by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people, was made by the .xii. apoſtels: &amp; though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> artycles therof, ar fermely &amp; ſtedfaſtly to be beleued of euery chryſten man, as artycles ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly proued by ſcripture yet that they were gathered togyder by the .xii. apoſtels: &amp; ſpecially that euery one of the apoſtels made one article, as paynters ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they dyd, can not be ꝓued by ſcripture, ne is not neceſſari to be beleued for our ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and though it were but a ſmal offence in the people
<pb facs="tcp:2407:5"/>
to beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it were an article neceſſarye to be beleued for our ſaluacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe the clergie, which be the lanternes &amp; le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders vnto the people, do inſtruct them that it is ſo: And it is nether agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of god, nor the lawe of reaſon, but that it may be ſo: yet it is a great offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the clergye, to afferme for certayne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyng, that is to them ſelfe vncertayne, and therfore it wold be reformed, for eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chewyng of offences vnto the clergye. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the people ſhal praye into the eſt is not proued by ſcripture: and yet they ſaye, that by the tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the apoſtles it is to be beleued. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lady was not borne in orygynal ſynne. That ſhe was aſſumpte into heuen body &amp; ſoule, Al theſe &amp; many other, diuers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie cal vnwrytten veryties, lefte in the worlde by the tradicion &amp; relacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the apoſtles, which as they ſaye, the people are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to beleue aſwel as ſcripture: For they ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſyth no man were bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de
<pb facs="tcp:2407:5"/>
to beleue ſcripture, but bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſayth, this is ſcripture: ſo they ſaye that in the thinges before reherſed, the chyrche wytneſſethe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be true, and that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people haue aſſented to them ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny yeres: wherfore it is not lawfull to doubte at them, ne to denye them: To thys reaſon it may be anſwered: that yf it can be proued by as good &amp; as hygh auctoryte, that theſe thynges were left in the world by the tradicion &amp; relacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the apoſtles, as the auctoryſynge of ſcripture was: that than they are to be beleued as verely as ſcripture: But yf they be wytneſſed to be ſo by ſome byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and prieſtes, and ſome other of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergye onely: or that they be witneſſed to be ſo by decrees &amp; lawes made by biſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome, &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergye of Rome or by opinion of doctours only: tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no man is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to accept them, ne beleue them, as they ar bounde to beleue ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture. For ſcripture, as it is ſayd before,
<pb facs="tcp:2407:6"/>
was auctoryſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole church of god and in the moſt electe &amp; mooſt gracious tyme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of lykelyhode hath ben ſyth the begynninge of chriſtes chyrche. And yf it be ſayd, that many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd opynio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haue ben affermed &amp; approued by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelles, in whom no errour maye be preſumed: it maye be anſwered: that though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrche gathered together in the holy ghoſt, may not erre in thinges perteyning to the fayth: that yet for as moch as ſom general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels haue ben gathered, &amp; not by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of kynges and princes, that be heades of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrch And that lawes haue ben alſo made at ſuch general co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels, of dyuers thinges whych haue not perteyned to the fayth but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayntenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the auctoritye or profyt of the clergye, or of ſoch arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles as ar before reherſed, that they cal vnwryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veryties, which vndoubtedly perteyn not merely to the faith. That it may therfore be lawfully doubted, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:2407:6"/>
ſoche cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels were gathered in the holy gooſt or not, &amp; whether they erred in theyr iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes or not, and it is no doubte, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in ſome general counſels they haue done ſo in dede. And I ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there be but fewe maters more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, ne more expedient for kynges &amp; princes to loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verytyes, &amp; of making of lawes by the clergie. For yf they be ſuffered to mayntayne that ther be any verytyes, whych the people are bounde to beleue vpon payne of dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beſyde ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, it wyl perſwade partly an inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencye in ſcripture, &amp; ther vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myght folowe greate daungers many wayes. And yf it were admytted, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergie myght be receaued to afferme that ther be ſoche veryties, beſyde ſcripture, yet they could not proue them. For yf they wold in profe therof ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the apoſtles fyrſt taught thoſe verities, &amp; that they haue ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one to another vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:2407:7"/>
thys daye, &amp; ſhewe none other aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytye therof but that: than al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayinge may as lyghtly be denyed, as it was af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fermed, and with as hygh auctorytye. And yf they wyl ferther attempte to ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proue it by lawes made by the biſhops of Rome, &amp; by the clergye at Rome: yea or by lawes &amp; decrees made at general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels: yet theſe lawes &amp; decrees may be lawfully doubted at, as before appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth: ſo that they cannot by reaſon ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of dryue any neceſſitye of belefe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to any perſon. Wherfore kynges and prynces y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue receaued of god the high power and charge ouer the people, ar bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to prohybyte ſoch ſayinges vpon greate paynes: and not to ſuffre a belefe to be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thynges vncerteyn. But yet yf ſome of the ſayd articlys that be called vnwrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verities were ſuffered to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue as thinges that be more like to be true, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwyſe: and no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of belefe to be deryued ther vpon.
<pb facs="tcp:2407:7"/>
I ſuppoſe verely it myght wel be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red that they ſhuld ſtand ſtyll not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habyte, as it is of that article y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the .xii. apoſtles made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crede: that it is good to praye into the eſt: that our lady was not borne in original ſynne: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe was aſſumpted bodye &amp; ſoule, And therfore yf it were ordeyned by kynges &amp; pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces that no man vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> payne, to be taken as a breaker of the quietnes of the people, ſhuld denye any of the ſayd articles: it were well done to kepe vnytie amonge the people: but diuers realmes may or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre ſoch thynges diuerſly, as they ſhall ſeme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenyent, after the dyſpoſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the people ther. For they be but thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to be beleued, or not beleued and ar nothing lyke to ſcripture, to the articles of the fayth, the .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ne to ſoch other morall lerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges as ar merely deryued out of ſcripture. For they muſt of neceſſitie be beleued &amp; obeyed of euery chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man. For after
<pb facs="tcp:2407:8"/>
ſaynt Paul ad Ephe. iiii. There muſte be one God, one fayth, &amp; one Baptiſme But to ſuffre them to ſtande as vnwry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten veryties, that may not be denyed: &amp; to haue theyr auctorytie onely by lawes made by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergie, it ſemeth dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous For it might cauſe many of the clergye to eſteme more power in the clergie tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is in dede: and that myghte lyfte many of them into a hygher eſtimacion of them ſelfe, than they ought to haue: wherby myght folowe greate daunger vnto the people. For as long as ther be diſorders in the clergye, it wyl be heard to bryng the people to good ordre. And all this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue touched before, maye be reformed, without any rebuke to the clergye that now is. For the pretence of ſoch vnwryten verytyes, ne yet of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of lawes, to bynde kynges &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and theyr people: ne yet that bothe powers, that is to ſaye, ſpiritual &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poral, were in the clergye, began not in
<pb facs="tcp:2407:8"/>
the clergye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now is, but in theyr prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours. And as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd other prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vnwryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verities, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld reſort to Rome, as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt high &amp; principal chyrche. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is a tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion &amp; an vnwryten verytie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ymages oughte to be ſet vp, it were wel done, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they &amp; ſoch other opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, wherby prdie couetyſe or vayne glory myght ſpringe her after, were prohabyte by auctoritie of the parlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te vpon great paynes. And as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd vnwryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verytie, that holy creame ſhuld be made after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye, it perteyneth only to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue auctoritie to iudge whether it be an vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wryten veritie, or not, and to iudge alſo what is the very auctoritye of making of that creame. And therfore I wyll no ferther ſpeke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter at thys tyme.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprinted at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſaynct An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes Paryſhe, in the Waredrop By Thomas Raynalde <hi>M.D.XLVIII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
